(桜井)う
Yes!
(日向･影山)しゃ
(田中)ナイス日向影山
Nice, Hinata, Kageyama!
That was so close. Shake it off, Ikejiri!
(駒木)惜しいドンマイ池尻
(芳賀)ナイスファイト
Nice try!
(入畑)ふむ
(溝口)烏野は使いませんね
Karasuno isn't using their set and blind fast attack.
例のトスを見ない速攻
(入畑)そのかわりか粗削りだが
In its place, although unpolished,
they've learned to use a normal fast attack.
普通の速攻が
使えるようになてる
ん
(入畑)下手くそながら
It's sloppy, but they're also adjusting trajectory.
コスの打ち分けまでしよる
ふこの短期間に
They must have had a really productive
practice match for it to happen this fast.
よほど有意義な練習試合でも
したかな
自分たちの武器を知り増やし
They have learned their own weapons and practiced them.
Now they utilize the best ones for each match.
その試合ごとに
ベストな攻撃で攻める
ふむいろんなことが
The precarious team that relied solely on power has gained wisdom.
力任せだた危ういチムに
知恵がついたか
(日向翔陽)あ
ピ
They still make a lot of basic errors.
でも相変わらず
凡ミスも多いですね
I'm sorry!
Receiving skills are the one thing you can't correct overnight.
レシブばかりは一朝一夕には
どうにもならんからな
(池尻)ナイサ茶屋
(玉川)一本
Give us a nice serve, Chaya!
Tokonami              Karasuno
One more!
Noya!
(田中)ノヤさん
(池尻)あ
ピ
(烏野一同)よしゃ
All right!
(金田一)あという間に
１セト目取りそうですね
They're suddenly about to win the set.
Their libero is going to be real trouble.
(岩泉)
あのリベロ相当厄介だぞ
Also, having that stubbled dude on their team
allows Kageyama to use his sets more effectively.
それにヒゲのあんちゃんが
入たおかげで
影山のトスも
前より幅が出せてる
(駒木)ドンマイ
(桜井)さ一本で切りましょう
Shake it off.
Come on, let's get one point and turn it around.
Right.
(澤村)もう一本
(池尻)ん
One more point!
(澤村)日向ナイサ頼むぞ
はい
Hinata, make it count!
Yes, sir!
We're taking this point!
(田中)一本取るぞ
おす
Yessir!
Episode Sixteen:
Winner and Loser
We did it!
((よしゃ
((やた
(池尻･ﾅﾚｰｼｮﾝ)＜中学最後の大会＞
It was our biggest tournament in junior high.
We seemed to win our first match by dumb luck.
＜まぐれみたいな
初めての初戦突破＞
Izumikan Jr. High
Furusan North Jr. High
Amado Jr. High
Taihaku Jr. High
Izumikan Jr. High
Furusan North Jr. High
Amado Jr. High
Taihaku Jr. High
But in the second round, we faced a team we didn't stand a chance against.
＜でも２回戦は
到底勝てるはずもない強豪校で
完全に諦めムドな俺たちに
お前言たよな＞
Do you remember what you told our team as we were giving up?
(澤村)((相手だて
同じ中学生なんだし
We're playing against junior high schoolers just like us,
絶対に勝てないなんてことない))
so losing isn't a sure thing!
((勝とうとしなきゃ勝てない
((めげねぇな澤村))
We can't win unless we try!
You never give up, Sawamura.
I'll never give up!
((めげてたまるか最後の大会だ))
This is my last tournament.
((相手も同じ中学生
We're playing against junior high schoolers just like us. You've got that right!
((確かにな))
((１回戦だて初めて勝たし
And we won in the first round for the first time!
(池尻)((よしゃ
２回戦も初勝ちするぞ
All right! We're gonna win in the second round for the first time as well!
Yeah!
(一同)((おお
((ピ
(太白一同)しゃ
Yes!
Our intentions were good, but naturally our team didn't suddenly improve.
(池尻)
＜それでもやぱり俺たちが
Izumikan                       Taihaku
突然強くなれるわけもなく＞
((ピ
(池尻)((悪い澤村))
Yes!
Sorry, Sawamura.
((ドン
(澤村)((すまん))
I'm sorry.
((この一本で切るぞ
This point will turn it around!
Izumikan                        Taihaku
(池尻)＜負けても
やぱりなぁて感じで
We lost, but it wasn't unexpected,
so it didn't hurt that much.
そんなに
悔しかた覚えもなかた＞
＜それまでの苦しい練習が
It even felt like a relief knowing that we wouldn't
have to do any more painful training the next day.
明日からはもうないんだて
解放感すらあて＞
((ん
＜でもお前一人だけ
苦しそうだたけど
But then there was you, the only one who was suffering.
なんでか俺はそんなふうなお前が
少し羨ましかた＞
I don't know why, but I felt a little jealous you could feel that way.
(駒木)あああ
あ
(烏野一同)しゃ
All right!
(玉川)だ大丈夫か池尻
ピ
A-Are you okay, Ikejiri?
(澤村)日向ナイサ
玉川
Hinata, give us a good serve!
Tamagawa!
(芳賀)ナイスレシブ玉川先輩
Nice receive, Tamagawa!
レフト来い
(芳賀)あ池尻先輩
Bring it left!
Ikejiri!
ピ
(烏野一同)しゃ
Tokonami              Karasuno
Yes!
(茶屋)はぁ
烏野噂と違うじゃねぇか
Karasuno is nothing like I've heard.
どこが堕ちた強豪だよ
(玉川)レベルが違うよな
They're really tough.
They're on a whole other level.
(澤村)((ネトを挟んだら
When the net stands between you,
superiority doesn't matter anymore!
格上とか格下とか関係ない
勝とうとしなきゃ勝てない
You can't win unless you try.
あいや今のは友達の
Uh, I mean...
My friend used to say...
(駒木)始まんぞ
(玉川･芳賀)おう
It's starting.
Right.
≪うわ俺なんかが言たて
It doesn't sound persuasive coming from a guy like me! Am I stupid?!
説得力ねぇだろバカか
≪完全に滑たろ俺うわ
I've totally lost it now.
(澤村)ナイサ影山
Give us a nice serve, Kageyama!
ダン
ノタチエス
All right!
An ace!
Now that they've won the first set,
Karasuno is starting to get into the groove.
１セト目取てますます
調子に乗り始めたな烏野は
ダン
ピ
All right!
Karasuno       Tokonami
≪くそ
Shit!
(桜井)あ
池尻
Ikejiri!
≪大きい≫
It's high!
よしゃ
(常波一同)よしゃ
Yes—
Yes!
Karasuno                         Tokonami
(茶屋)たた１点で
俺ら喜びすぎじゃね
Aren't we going a little overboard over one point?
(駒木)
いいんだよこういう１点から
That's how it should be.
This is the kind of point that turns the tide!
流れが来るんだよ
みんな
Guys.
(玉川)
勝とうとしなきゃ勝てない
We can't win unless we try, right?
よな
(茶屋)食らいついてくぞ
We'll be tenacious!
A small-time team knows how to hang in there!
(駒木)弱小だて
粘るときは粘るんだ
Let's go for the win!
勝ちに行くぞ
おお
Yeah!
アヤ
(アヤ)う
Aya!
結お願い
(道宮)はい
Yui, get it!
Right!
く
アウト
Let it go!
ピ
(白戸一同)よし
Yes!
(白戸女子)ナイスジャジ
(白戸応援団)Ｌ･Ｕ･Ｃ･Ｋ･Ｙ
Nice judgment call!
L, U, C, K, Y! L, U, C, K, Y! Lucky!
Shirato Girls                Karasuno
Ｌ･Ｕ･Ｃ･Ｋ･Ｙラキ
(澤村)((勝てるて確信が
持てなくても周りの連中に
Even if you're not sure you can win,
or everyone around you says you don't stand a chance,
絶対無理だて言われても
俺たちは
we can't...
ふん
(２人)え
≪｢俺たちだけは
それを言たらダメだろう｣≫
We can't allow ourselves to say that!
ピ
(白戸女子)ナイサ
Give us a good serve!
Go!
(白戸応援団)行け
(道宮)アヤ
Aya!
ピ
(白戸一同)やた
We did it!
(道宮)
ドンマイドンマイ惜しいよ
Shake it off, Aya! You almost had it!
You could've retrieved that, Yui.
(アヤ)結なら今の拾えてたな
(道宮)え
What?
I'm sorry! I've messed up so many balls!
ごめん私何本も失敗して
(道宮)反省は試合終わてから
Reflect on the match after it's over.
Now, stand up.
さあ立てまだ終わてない
This isn't over yet!
ピ
(烏野一同)よしゃ
All right!
Karasuno             Tokonami
≪烏野は余裕のマチポイント
向こうからしたら
Match point, fully in Karasuno's favor.
For them, it won't hurt in the least if they lose this point.
痛くもかゆくもない
１点かもしれないけど
But for us...
≪俺たちには
≪もう１点≫
One more point.
≪まだ
It isn't over!
(一同)≪来い烏野
Come and get us, Karasuno!
Sakurai!
桜井
(芳賀)池尻先輩
Ikejiri!
≪まだ負けてない
We haven't lost this yet!
≪まだ終わてない
This isn't over yet!
レフト
Left!
ピ
(一同)よしゃ
Right on!
You pieces of shit!
(西谷)くそがぁ
I'll retrieve the next one!
(西谷)次はぜてぇ拾う
(澤村)一本取り返すぞ
(烏野一同)おお
We're gonna get that point back!
Yeah!
≪ああこいつら本気だ≫
These guys are playing for keeps.
(池尻)≪たぶんこの会場で
In this venue where our team isn't even on anyone's radar, I'll bet...
The Iron Wall of Date
誰も注目も警戒もしてない
俺たちに
(池尻)≪こいつらだけが
these guys are the only ones...
(池尻)≪本気だ≫
playing us for keeps.
ピ
Karasuno
(影山飛雄)
おいボケとしてんなボケ
Snap out of it, dumbass! Get movi—
ささと
勝た
We won.
おう
次
Yeah.
Does that mean we get another match?
次も試合ある
Yeah, 'cause we won.
おう勝たからな
勝た
We won.
We won!
We can play another match!
次もまた試合ができる
コトに立ていられる次も
We can stay on the court!
For another match!
(武田)勝利に飢えた小さな獣が
The tiny beast, so hungry for victory,
初めて勝利の味を知たんですね
(繋心)ああ
has had his very first taste.
Yeah.
(金田一)あいつら午後に
もうひと試合あるてこと
Are these guys fully aware they have
another match to play this afternoon?
分かてんすかね
ん
It's just that victory was a sure thing, so they should've kept as much energy in reserve as possible.
だてあそこまでいたら
逆転はないんだし
なるべく
体力を温存しといた方が
What's so bad about it?
(及川)
よかたじゃん本気が見れてさ
We got to see them play for keeps.
But they didn't use the deviant fast attack.
でも変人速攻はやんなかたね
(花巻)向こうのコトも終わた
伊達工の圧勝だ
The other match is also over.
Date Tech won by a landslide.
Karasuno vs. Date Tech.
(金田一)烏野対伊達工か
どちが勝ち上がてきますかね
Who will rise to the top?
(岩泉)行くぞ
俺たちも次勝たなきゃ
Let's go.
We have to secure our next victory or we won't be there.
そこに行けないんだ
Prefectural
High School
Girls Volleyball
Tournament
Prefectural
High School
Girls Volleyball
Tournament
(アヤ)うぅ
(道宮)泣かないでよもう
Stop crying, you silly!
(アヤ)
だて私がサブで狙われて
I can't help it. They went after my serves.
いぱい点取られて
ううぅ
They took so many points because of me.
それを繋いでくのがバレじゃん
Volleyball is about keeping the ball in play after that!
Our opponents were better at it
than we were! That's why we lost.
相手の方がそれがうまかた
だから負けた
The blame doesn't fall on any one person!
誰のせいとかそういうのない
うぅ
キャプテン先生が呼んでます
(道宮)うん
Captain, the teacher wants to see you.
Right!
I'll be right back, okay?
ちょと行てくるからね
(烏野女子)
道宮先輩すごいですね
Michimiya is incredible.
いちばん練習して
いちばん悔しいはずなのに
She practiced the most,
so why isn't she taking it the hardest?
違う
え
She is.
What?
(烏野女子)
ああやてみんなの前では
She keeps up a strong front when she's with us.
ちゃんと主将でいて
Is the next match after that one?
一人になて
うちらに背を向けてから
She'll wait until she's alone.
≪俺にしては頑張たよな≫
I actually did a pretty good job.
I didn't skip practice that much.
≪それなりに
サボらずやたし
テレビで試合を見た次の日は
The day after I saw the match on TV, I goofed off,
ふざけてでも半分本気で
but I was half serious when I said I'd be representing Japan in the future.
将来は日本代表になるとか
言たりして
そのくせ
地味な筋トレになた途端に
But the moment it came down to boring resistance training,
my enthusiasm bottomed out.
テンション下がたりして≫
≪これで終わりか早かたな≫
Is this all there is?
That was quick.
≪まだ６月だぞ≫
It's only June.
≪あのときもう少し
If only I'd worked just a little harder at it back then...
もう少しだけ頑張てたら
If only I'd worked a little harder at the resistance training and running...
(池尻)≪筋トレも走り込みも
もと頑張てたら
(道宮)≪もと
主将らしくできてたら
If only I'd been more of a captain...
If only I'd been a little more desperate to make one more receive...
(池尻)≪レシブ１本に
もと必死になれてたら
(道宮)≪あと一歩
足が前に出ていたなら
If only I'd gotten in one more step...
(池尻)≪もう少しもう少し
バレをやれていたんだろうか≫
Would I have gotten to play volleyball just a little longer?
≫(池尻)澤村
ん
Sawamura!
はぁはぁはぁ
池尻
Ikejiri?
勝てよたくさん勝てよ
Win!
You have to keep winning!
俺たちの分も
Win for us too!
(澤村)ああ受け取た
Sure.
Challenge accepted!
≪たぶんこんなふうに
あけなく部活を終わるヤツが
Tens of thousands of players nationwide are probably
going through the same match-ending disappointment.
全国に何万人といるんだろう
何試合もある予選を
全部勝ち抜いて
To get to nationals, they have to win every single preliminary match.
全国へ行て
これがフィクションだとしたら
If this were a work of fiction,
全国へ行くヤツらが主役で
the guys going to nationals would be the main characters,
and we would be like the fill-in characters.
俺たちはエキストラみたいな
感じだろうか
それでも
But so what?
≪俺たちもやたよ≫
We were a part of that.
≪私たちもやてたよ≫
(池尻･道宮)≪バレボル≫
Volleyball.
Haikyuu !!
≪(観客たち)わあ
≫(他校生)すごかたなぁ烏野
Karasuno was incredible.
≫(他校生)特に
あの小さい１０番にはビビた
Their tiny number ten really freaked me out!
Yeah, that's for sure.
≫(他校生)ああだよな
速攻すげぇ決まてたもんな
He was totally nailing those fast attacks.
ななんだよ
うれしくたていいじゃんか
Wh-What? I'm allowed to be happy!
俺あんなふうに
言われたことないし
No one's ever said that kind of stuff about me before.
ふ
え
別に何も言てねぇだろ
Did I say anything?
It's great that you're getting noticed.
お前が注目されんのは
いいことじゃねぇか
相手がお前に注目して
警戒すればするほど
The more our opponents notice you and get defensive around you,
お前は本領を発揮する
the more you can tap into your potential.
おおよく分かんないけど
I'm not sure what you're saying,
but for now, your smile terrifies me.
とりあえずお前の笑顔が怖い
うあ痛たたた
(繋心)おうそのとおりだな
Ow!
Yeah, he's right.
とにかくあのちこい１０番が
すげぇ的な空気を作る
Anyway, "that tiny number ten" will set an excellent mood.
それが大きくなればなるほど
The brighter the mood is,
日向が光れば光るほど
相手のブロクは目がくらむのさ
and the more Hinata shines, the more it will blind the opponent blockers.
(繋心)
で２回戦のスタティングは
We'll be using the same starting lineup for round two as we did for round one.
１回戦ときと同じでいく
次の試合は１時半からだ
The next match is at 1:30 PM.
Don't let yourselves cool down.
体冷やすなよ
それまでに軽く飯食とけ
Have a light meal before that time.
腹いぱいにはすんなよ
(一同)うす
Don't fill up!
Yessir!
次あの眉なしのいる
鉄壁高校だな
Our next match is against No Brow's Iron Wall high school.
伊達工業な
分かてるし
That's Date Tech.
I knew that!
たぶん伊達工に負けたていう
３月の試合が
I think that the match Karasuno lost to Date Tech in March
東峰さんが部を離れた原因だ
あ旭さんが
is the reason why Azumane quit the team.
Really?
(菅原)((ある試合で旭のスパイクは
徹底的にブロクに止められてさ))
There was a match in which the opposition blocked all of his spikes.
あの旭さんを
徹底的に止めたブロク
Blockers that can completely stop Asahi from scoring.
Hinata, Kageyama.
(菅原)日向影山
あ
(菅原)ちょといいか
Have you got a minute?
(澤村)旭
Asahi.
そろそろ行くぞ
We should get going.
(菅原)よろしく頼む
I'm counting on you.
伊達工業は強敵だ
Date Tech is a strong opponent.
３か月前はあの鉄壁のブロクに
コテンパンにやられた
Three months ago, they thrashed us good with their Iron Wall block.
But now we have our greatest decoy!
(菅原)でも今は最強の囮がいる
日向の前の道を
切り開いたみたいに
You blazed a trail for Hinata to use.
旭の
Now, I want you to blaze a path for our ace, Asahi!
エスの前の道も切り開いてくれ
よしゃ２回戦も勝つぞ
All right! We're gonna win round two as well!
ああ
(田中)え
ゴゴレツゴ
レツゴ伊達工
Go, go, let's go! Let's go, Date Tech!
(伊達工応援団)ゴゴ
レツゴレツゴ伊達工
The Iron Wall of Date
ゴゴレツゴ
レツゴ伊達工
Date Tech, fight!
(茂庭)伊達工ファイ
Yeah!
Running!
(茂庭)ランニング
(伊達工一同)オエオエ
(田中)ビビるのに忙しいヤツだな
伊達工怖ぇ
Those guys sure keep busy with scare tactics!
Date Tech scares me.
一緒のコトにいたら
のまれるわ
They'd overwhelm anyone sharing the same court.
１回戦で伊達工と
当たてたチムのスパイカ
I felt so bad for the spiker on the team they played in the first round.
すげぇかわいそうだたよな
(他校生)文字どおり
It was like they literally won't cut any slack for anyone.
何もさせてもらえないて
感じだたもんな
キャプテン
Captains!
(茂庭･澤村)
よろしくお願いします
Let's have a good match.
The Iron Wall of Date
レツゴ伊達工
(武田)なんていうかコト全体が
伊達工色て感じですね
It's like the entire stadium wants Date Tech to win.
(澤村)先レシブになりました
We're receiving first.
コトはこちで
おう
We're on this side.
Right.
(澤村)アプだレシブ
(一同)おす
Warm up! Receiving!
Yessir!
Let's do this! Keep it in play!
行くぞ繋げよ
(一同)うす
Yessir!
≪伊達工に
ストレト負けしてから
It's been three months since we lost in straight sets to Date Tech.
たた３か月か
チムは確実に進化していても
２３年の中のどかにはまだ
The team is definitely evolving, but the image of losing may linger in the heads of the upperclassmen.
負けるイメジが
居座てるのかもしれねぇな≫
≪とりあえずこの
伊達工にのまれ気味な空気を
For now, we need to do something about this intimidating atmosphere.
なんとかしねぇと
Rolling...
(西谷)ロリング
あ
Thunder...
サンダアゲイン
Again!
へへ決またぜ
Nailed it.
(田中)ノヤさんナイスレシブ
キレキレじゃねぇか技名以外
Noya, nice receive!
You're totally sharp! Aside from the name.
The name is sharp too!
技名もキレキレだろうが
教えてアゲインも教えて
Teach it to me! Teach me how to do the "Again"!
前のと何が違うんですか
(月島･山口)ぷぷ何あれ
Was that different from the last one?
What was that?
Just receive it normally.
(菅原)普通に拾えただろ
(澤村)また西谷は
Nishinoya's up to it again.
Psst, Nishinoya! Daichi will get mad at you again.
(東峰)
こら西谷また大地に怒られるよ
よしゃ
心配することなんかなんもねぇ
All right! We've got nothing to worry about!
(一同)あ
(西谷)みんな前だけ見てけよ
You guys focus on what's in front!
背中は俺が守てやるぜ
I've got your backs.
(３人)カカコいい
Th...
That's so cool!
That's so cool.
なんとみんなの空気が
いつもどおりになりましたね
I'll be dammed!
It looks like everyone's in the usual frame of mind now.
Yeah.
For all that stature, he's incredibly reliable.
≪小さい体で
なんつう頼もしさ
守備だけじゃない
リベロの重要な仕事は
A libero not only defends the team.
Another vital part of the job is to support the team from behind the scenes.
コトの後ろからの
チムの鼓舞≫
本当に優秀なリベロだな
He really is an excellent libero.
Fly
The Iron Wall of Date
(澤村･茂庭)整列
Fly
The Iron Wall of Date
Form a line!
Fly
The Iron Wall of Date
(一同)お願いします
Let's have a good match!
Next Episode Preview
So you were stumped by No Brows once before, Asahi?
前回はあの眉なしに
止められたんですよね旭さん
Huh? Yeah.
(東峰)ううん
なんか威圧感あるよなぁ
He is kind of intimidating.
But you're more than a match for him when it comes to looking old!
でも年齢不詳感じゃ
負けてないすよ
What?
(東峰)ええ
(菅原)もうやめてあげて
Please stop!
Episode Seventeen:
The Iron Wall
Next time on Haikyuu!!:
"The Iron Wall."